Hello class, this lecture will
focus on antiarrhythmic drugs.
So in this lecture, I will
begin with a brief review
of the action potential,
because many of these drugs
will affect either
depolarization or repolarization.
I will also consider the
adverse effects, because
as you will come to
see, some of these drugs
themselves can be pro
-arrhythmic. So it may be
necessary to evaluate
the patient and assess do
they need medication or
can this issue be managed
with a pacemaker or
ablation or cardioversion.
And then I will also discuss
some of the miscellaneous
medications that we use
for arrhythmias. And among
them will be drugs like
digoxin or adenosine, or
even giving ions themselves,
whether it be potassium
or even magnesium for
torsades or digoxin toxicity.
So, with the action
potential, you can see on the
left side, where we begin
with the upstroke from phase
0 to 1, that is the opening
of the sodium channels,
and you will now have the
influx of positive charge
causing depolarization. So
the drugs that are considered
to be sodium channel blockers
will have some impact
on depolarization,
especially the 1A and the 1C.
When we have the sodium
entering the cell, the
channels will become
inactivated. They'll close,
and there we will begin
initial repolarization.
At phase 2, we will begin
now to have an opening
of the calcium channel,
and that allows for
calcium entry, and that is
really where we have the
plateau or the shoulder
of the action potential.
And the drugs that we know as
class 4 calcium
channel blockers,
rapamil and dultiazem,
will work in this area.
So in phase three,
the calcium channels
begin to close, and now we have
the opening of the
potassium channel.
And now potassium takes over,
and we get repolarization.
And this now should
make sense because
repolarization,
depending on potassium,
would mean sort of
the rest for the cell.
Okay, potassium is the ion
of rest. And then phase
4, which really corresponds
a lot to automaticity
and will be the site of
action in the pacemaker.
And drugs like beta
blockers and calcium
channel blockers
fill nicely here
because they reduce
the slope of phase 4.
What you start to
get is a reset. You
start to reset all
the ions, sodium,
calcium, and potassium.
And that is achieved
through the anteport
mechanism that involves
the sodium and calcium
exchanger. And remember,
with that exchange
mechanism, for every
three sodium that comes
back in, one calcium
will come out. Now,
EKG is important
because we know that
these drugs, given
their mechanism, will
have subtle changes
shown on the EKG.
So, the P wave corresponds
to the atrium, and you'll
see that this might be
changed in the situation of
maybe an atrial fibrillation
or an atrial flutter.
So the PR interval
corresponds to the movement
of the action potential
from the atria through
the AV node. And the AV
node is very important.
That's the atrial ventricular
node. And I like to
say that this AV node
is almost like a filter.
It slows the impulse.
without the AV node, you
probably will see patients
having heart rates upward
into the three or four
hundreds. So if there's
an issue with the AV node,
that is a big problem.
QRS is the ventricular
depolarization. So when I
think of that, I think of
sodium. And the QRS duration
really stands for the fact
where all the ventricular
cells become activated.
And this will be important
to evaluate when we do the
sodium channel blockers.
The T wave represents
ventricular repolarization.
So you have to associate the
T wave and repolarization
somewhat with potassium.
and it makes sense.
Patients that have
hypokalemia, maybe
due to the fact
that they're taking
diuretics like
thiazides or loops,
they will probably
have, in low potassium
states, slower repolarization.
And that really
shows as a decreased
T-wave on the EKG.
with hyperkalemia which is
attributed to ACE inhibitors
ARBs and maybe spironolactone
you're going to
get a slowering of
conduction and a decrease in
action potential duration
and that sometimes on an EKG
will show as a peaked T
wave and then lastly QT is
the duration of the
ventricular action potential.
Increase in QT can happen
with medications, especially
if we're prolonging
repolarization, and that has
to do with some degree of
potassium channel blockade.
You'll see this happening
with the drugs of the 1A
antiarrhythmic class, and
you'll also see it to an
extent with the class 3
potassium channel blockers.
The other time that QT
can be an issue is, of
course, those people that
have a genetic long QT. In
those cases, they need to
get that resolved somehow,
whether it be through
ablation or through another
type of method. And
remember, when we talk about
this idea of ventricular
tachycardia, ventricular
fibrillation, they're
both serious, but V-fib is
probably the worst, where the
impulses become so chaotic
that the patient can end
up in cardiac arrest.
There are three main mechanisms
of arrhythmias. Number
one is going to be an increase
in automaticity. And I
tend to think that this is
coming from the pacemaker.
Mostly we see the
issue happening in
phase four of the
action potential.
What I will say here,
this is usually,
what's usually involved
is norepinepirin
binding to the beta
receptors in the heart.
and when you have that
happening of course you're
going to get an increase in
heart rate from the pacemaker
and you will also have
some degree of AV node
enhancement. So when you give
the patient whether a beta
blocker or you give a calcium
channel blocker such as
rapamil and you will decrease
the slope of phase 4.
And that will change now
the whole idea of your rate.
Triggered, the
most likely reasons
for this type of arrhythmia
is either from an early
after depolarization, which
tends to happen around phase
3 of the action potential.
I will say that the most
common reasons for this is
a situation of hypokalemia
and a lowered heart rate.
Delayed after depolarization
happens right here, after
phase 4 of the action
potential. And we tend to
see that the mechanism here
is high levels of calcium
influx. It can happen
through that because maybe of
a digoxin toxicity, and
you'll see a little bit later,
or those patients who have
had an ischemic event.
And the reentry is
pretty straightforward in
explanation. is that the
impulse goes through the
heart and it excites the
pathway and then for some
reason it goes back and
re-excites that pathway.
Probably the best example
would be the situation
of atrial fibrillation
or atrial flutter.
But there's also certain
heart conditions like Wolf
-Parkinson's White where
there may be the formation
of an accessory pathway,
such as the bundle of Kent.
So we'll talk about the
medical management of
Wolff-Parkinson's White
at the end of the lecture.
So this is the classification
of antiarrhythmic
drugs that is in the textbook.
It's known as the Vaughan
-Williams classification,
where there is four
major classes and then
miscellaneous. and that would
include drugs like the
doxin, adenosine, magnesium.
Class 1 antiarrhythmics
will all block the sodium
channels. So there will be,
especially with the 1A and
the 1C, a definite change
with depolarization. Okay,
so 1A, as you can see, you're
getting some prolongation
of depolarization, and
that has to do with
blockage of the sodium
channels, and that would be
attributed now on the EKG
to an increase in QRS.
1A also blocks potassium
channels and that would
mean that you are prolonging
as you can see here
repolarization as you can
see in the red line and
that will increase QT
so that is one mechanism
by which the 1As themselves
can be proarrhythmic
The other thing is that
the three drugs in this
group do have muscarinic
receptor blockade.
M2 receptors are in the heart.
If you block those receptors,
you're turning on sympathetics.
And what you're going to
see is an increase in AV
node action. Okay, so with
many of them, especially
disopiramide, you will
likely have to pair that
up with an AV node suppressant
like a beta blocker.
1B is interesting
in that you're going
to not have much going on with
depolarization, as you
can see in this line.
and that makes sense because
1B drugs like lidocaine
are given in situations
where the tissue has
already been depolarized
and the biggest example of
that is in a ischemic episode
so lidocaine is usually
given post MI in the hours
post MI to prevent that
patient from having a
possible ventricular event.
The other thing that makes
it so nice is, as you
can see, there is no effect
on the potassium channels.
As a matter of fact, as
you see, you're getting
a shortening of the
action potential, and that
would lower the QT, and
that makes it, again, very
important in those patients
that have had an MI.
In depolarized cells,
this mechanism will
slow the conduction.
And that's very
important post-MI.
1C, as you can envision
here, this is the one
with the most prolongation
of depolarization.
And you see that
green line shifting to
the right, more so
definitely than the 1A.
And this group is going
to enhance QRS. And that
itself in certain
patients can be an issue
because if you're increasing
that interval, you're
activating the ventricular
cells. So you need to
give this in certain
cases, and I'll speak about
it in a moment. But with
respect to prolonging
the action potential or
shortening it, it doesn't.
So as you can see,
there's no effect on QT.
One thing I want to
bring up is last semester
we discussed antidepressants,
the tricyclics.
And we said that they
used to be used before
the SSRIs, but they
have autonomic effects.
And what we are concerned
with in an overdose,
say, of amitriptyline is
that it is cardiotoxic.
And if you look at how
that happens, it kind of
mimics what's happening
with the 1A sodium channel
blockers. Those patients
on an EKG that have
overdosed will have a high
QRS and a high QT. And
that is why, with respect
to managing an overdose
of a tricyclic, we give
sodium bicarbonate itself
to stabilize the sodium
channels of the heart.
Class I drugs are use
-dependent. And this is
an interesting concept
where you're going to
get more of an inhibition
of depolarization on
those cells that are
frequently depolarizing.
That means that those
patients that have
tachycardia or faster
heart rates are going
to have increased
sodium channel block.
And that is known
as use dependence.
So, in identifying these drugs,
First Aid puts it
nicely, and I have
adapted it from them,
that the queen prefers
discos, and that
would mean quinidine,
percanamide, and disopiramide.
So these drugs will
block the open sodium
channels, and they're
going to slow the 0 to 1.
And you can see that the
line is shifted to the right.
And they're also, with the
fact that they're blocking
potassium channels, they're
going to also prolong
the action potential. They
also prolong the refractory
period. Now, the refractory
period is the time
it takes for the sodium
channels to recover from being
activated and then a new
impulse to be generated.
These drugs will treat both
atrial and ventricular
arrhythmias
Due to the effect on the
sodium channels, you're
going to get an increase
in QRS. And because of the
block of the potassium
channels, you will enhance QT.
So that is the
proarrhythmic action.
Again, I mentioned
these drugs will also
block the M2 receptors
in the heart. And
that's going to
increase AB node action.
Quinidine has its
own adverse effects.
It comes from quinine,
which was found in
the bark of the
cinchona tree. It was
used in missionary
times to reduce fevers.
And patients that use quinine,
say for P. falciparum malaria,
will develop cinchonism.
And the same can be
true for quinidine, where
there'll be headache,
dizziness, and
tinnitus developed.
And tinnitus is
the ear ringing.
The other drug that
we discussed that can
cause this early on in
its toxicity is aspirin.
The other thing about
quinidine is that
it does have some
immune-like actions.
for the platelets
antibodies can develop and
attack the glycoproteins
on the platelets so
the patient may show
on their cbc decreased
platelets they may experience
bleeding in the liver
there is also an
immune reaction and the
patient can develop changes
in their skin fever,
right upper quadrant
pain. What this would
mean is that you
remove the medication.
Procanamide. I would say
we are expecting the same
adverse effects with the
high QT and the M2 block.
The other thing with this
medication is that
there can be a
a decrease in peripheral
vascular resistance, which
means hypotension. And
the reason being is the
fact that there is some
block of the alpha receptors.
So you can see a lowering
of blood pressure with
procainamide. The other
thing with procainamide
is that along with
hydrolyzine, the vasodilator,
and isoniazid, which will
you see for tuberculosis,
it exhibits a phase
two metabolism, which
involves, in this
case, acetylation.
If you acetylate quickly,
you won't get drug therapy,
therapeutic benefit,
the proper term. If you
metabolize slowly, you
build up the drug and
the patient can experience
arthralgias and,
of course, this
presentation of butterfly
rash. And this is known
as drug-induced lupus.
Dysopiramide is the one
of the three that has the
most muscarinic block, most
atropine-like. So, thinking
about atropine being a
muscarinic blocker, you're
going to get the urinary
retention, the medriasis,
the tachycardia,
the constipation,
and the dry mouth, eyes, etc.
The other thing is,
since you're having an
increase in AV node
action, you want to give
this with an AV node
suppressant. And as
mentioned, probably the
one that they would use
the most is the beta
-1 block or metoprolol.
So just to review
receptor physiology,
acetylcholine binds to the
M2 receptors in the heart.
And what takes over is the
G-inhibitory mechanism.
Now G-inhibitory means
everything slows down. You're
getting a decrease in
adenyl cyclase, a decrease
in cyclic AMP, and what results
is negative chronotropic,
that means a lowering
of heart rate, and a
negative dromotropic, which
would mean that you're
reducing the speed of the
impulse through the AV node.
That makes sense. When
we treat patients with
Alzheimer's with
rivastigmine, being the fact
that it's an acetylcholine
esterase inhibitor,
one of the issues that
we worry about is that,
is this patient going
to become bradycardic?
Okay, makes sense.
Same thing with
organophosphate
poisoning, because those
drugs seek to raise
acetylcholine.
The way we manage is
by giving a blocker.
and sometimes you'll see
later in the lecture and
in my packets I did allude
to the fact that for
bradycardia you can give
atropine but I will say that
atropine yes will bring
the heart rate up and we
don't want to be either
extreme whether it be brady
or tachycardic but you
have to do this dose this
carefully because there's
been times when atropine is
given and then the patient
goes into tachycardia.
So next we have the 1B. We have
lidocaine and we have mexotine.
Not much happening
with the depolarization
because as I mentioned,
these are the drugs
that work on tissue that
has been depolarized.
But you'll see that
they're shortening
the action potential
and that is
appropriate, it will
decrease QT interval.
When we're talking about
the channels, as I said
before, the 1A works
mainly on the open
channels. These will work
on the inactivated channels
and the inactivated
channel effect means that
there's going to be
greater effects in the
ventricles and again,
that's another good thing
if we have a patient who
had a recent MI. why?
Lidocaine is given
intravenously.
And by the way, as a
review, this is an amide
anesthetic. So if you're
going to the dentist to
remove the wisdom tooth,
they'll give you that locally.
Anybody who, you know,
gets muscle rubs from
the pharmacy, they do
have some of those rubs
that have lidocaine
in it. You can get it
as a patch as well to
numb some of the pain.
So the point here is, if
we gave too much lidocaine
intravenously, the patient
can have neurological
effects. They can get
paresthesias, which are tingling in
the extremities, or in
worst case scenario, they
could get seizures. So again,
be mindful of that, and
also other medications,
because being a substrate for
SIP, it can be inhibited
or induced by those drugs,
say an azole, will
inhibit its metabolism
and raise lidocaine's
concentration.
Mexaltine is oral. It
does have some GI effects.
And phenytoin is also
put in the group.
You won't be giving
phenytoin on the floors
for this purpose, but
it's important to know
that it does have some
1B actions. And remember,
phenytoin does have
the effects that it
can cause hirsutrism,
excessive hair growth,
gingival hyperplasia,
just like the calcium
channel blockers, and
nystagmus, where the patient
will have some degree
of change in their eyes.
So 1C, they will work
also on the open channel
just like the 1A,
but with respect to
depolarization, there's going
to be greater depolarization
expected with the 1C.
and you can see that
the line here has
shifted way to the right.
The other thing that it
doesn't share with the
other two in its class is
that not much is happening
with the action potential,
as you can see here.
One thing about this
group, when they bind to
the channel, they exhibit
slow, unbinding kinetics.
So they come off the
channel rather slowly.
and here is the important
thing with these medications
is that given the fact that
they prolong the depolarization
significantly, they're
going to raise the QRS
significantly and that can
increase the ventricular
activation and the ventricular
rate. So these are reserved
for patients that have
refractory ventricular
arrhythmias, in some cases of
AFib, but the kicker here is
you do not want to give this
to patients that have had
structural damage to their
heart, such as somebody who
had an MI, because this
ventricular rate can be an
issue. And we do have data
from a study known as CAST,
cardiac arrhythmia
suppression trial, where
they gave flecainide to
patients that had an MI,
and those that had a
certain degree of structural
damage did have a
greater risk of dying.
The other thing is that
these drugs are negative
inotropic. so inotropic
effects means effects on heart
contraction negative
inotropic means you're getting
a decrease in contraction
if you are somebody with
a congestive heart failure
where you're already
not getting an appropriate
heart pumping ability
anything negative inotropic
is going to make it worse.
And then the other
thing is flecainide.
Blocks the ryanidine receptor.
Now we talked about
ryanidine receptors when
we discussed dantraline
and the skeletal muscle.
And we said that patients
who take D2 blockers,
pure D2 blockers,
like the typical
antipsychotics, are at a
greater risk of getting NMS.
And remember, that
was the lead pipe
rigidity with the
high temperature.
And that temperature was
coming through sustained
muscle contraction.
So we gave dantrolene
and that had an effect
on the ryanidine receptor
and that stopped the
shifting of the calcium
that is needed for skeletal
muscle contraction.
It seems to be that flecainide
can do the same thing
in the heart by blocking
those receptors in the heart.
And that has been studied to be
effective at those
patients that have
catecholamine
ventricular tachycardia.
Class 2 are the beta blockers.
And as mentioned, these
drugs can work in the
pacemaker, the SA node
and the AV node. They
will suppress there.
we are looking at phase
4 of the action potential
where you're going
to get a decrease in
the slope of phase 4.
And calcium channel
block layers,
mainly verapamil and diltiazem,
can do the same thing.
So all the beta receptors,
and here I'm talking
about specifically in
the heart is beta 1,
will work at G-stimulatory.
norepinephrine binds to
that receptor in the heart
it increases adhenyl
cyclase and then cyclic AMP
and protein kinase A
calcium will shuttle in and
that's going to cause
contraction of the heart
that's going to raise heart
rate and cardiac output
so when you give a beta
1 blocker like metoprolol
all of that is going
to stop and now you're
getting a decrease in heart
rate and cardiac output
and there we go we've seen
this slide before the other
thing to note that in the
jugsular glomerular apparatus
in the kidney there is a
beta-1 receptor if you give
metoprolol there's some
indirect action at binding
renin so even though it's
not the same action of an ACE
inhibitor or an R because
those are more direct, you
can have some decrease in
renin from a beta blocker.
They'll suppress
the AV node and the
SA nodes, and these
are all the uses,
very big drug class
in cardiology.
In thyrotoxicosis or thyroid
storm, the patient
is hyperthyroid.
Of course, we want to give
something like methimazole
to treat hyperthyroidism.
But in some cases, we
have to be worried about
the patient's heart rate.
In thyroid storm, the
patient's heart rate can
go so high that they're
at risk of getting an
arrhythmia before the
antithyroid drugs kick in.
So for first choice, we
want to give a beta blocker.
beta 1 selective metoprolol
atenolol the non-selectives
mean that they block beta 2
and that is going to cause
bronchoconstriction hypoglycemia
because you're going
to block the conversion
conversion of glycogen to
glucose and then PVD peripheral
vascular disease if you
block beta 2 receptors there,
you're going to get the
patient having a worsening
of their vasoconstriction.
Pindolol, Asputolol are
intrinsic sympathomimetic.
So they're partial
agonists. They can actually
kick up sympathetics
and can worsen ischemia.
And then Esmolol is
ultra-short-acting,
can be used intravenously
in the hospital.
So class 3 potassium
channel blockers, when we
look at the action potential,
we see that it does
resemble the 1A sodium
channel blockers in that
there's a prolongation of
repolarization. However,
unlike the 1A, there's no
effects on depolarization.
Commonly used to treat AFib,
AFlutter, and
ventricular tachycardia,
the idea that they're
prolonging the action
potential would mean
that they are going
to increase QT and
perhaps trussades,
and they exhibit a
reverse use dependence.
And this is interesting.
It's now the opposite of
use dependence. Use dependence,
we're thinking about
the drug having a greater
effect on those with
tachycardia. reverse use
means that they're going to
work more these potassium
channel blockers in patients
that have a slower rate
which would mean that those
patients are going to
be more sensitive to the
repolarization and more
likely have an increase in QT
there's four drugs to
consider the main one is
amiodarone we have abutilide,
dofidilide, and sodalol
Amiodarone, quite
possibly, is the
biggest antiarrhythmic
of all because
we consider it to
be broad spectrum.
And that means
that in addition to
having the potassium
channel block,
there's a degree of sodium,
calcium, and also beta and
alpha receptor blockade.
so you may see
hypotension with this one
there is a lower incidence
of QT even though
we have the repolarization
happening and the
reason being is that it
has beta blockade on board
so that can help with
that ventricular event
and meodorone is
a substrate for
CYP3A4. So that means
it can be inhibited
or induced by any
of those drugs.
Itself, it can inhibit other
medications like digoxin,
warfarin, and statins.
So with the warfarin, if
you inhibit warfarin, you
may be more prone to bleed.
The drug has a long half-life,
average 60 days, and
it makes a metabolite,
desethylamiodarone,
which in the
liver can inhibit
fatty acid oxidation.
There can be some increase
in lipid production,
and that can, in fact,
affect the mitochondria.
And of course, there is
formation of ROSs as well.
as I as I show you
there at iodine this
medication is iodinated as
you can see here there's
iodine groups in the
drug structure if
you have iodine you
can create more thyroid
hormone and that can
lead to hyperthyroidism.
The other thing is that in the
mechanism that makes
thyroid hormone,
there needs to be a
conversion of T4 to T3.
T3 is the active that
goes to the nuclear
receptor and does the
job of what we need
thyroid hormone to be
for us in our bodies.
If that is blocked by
amiodarone, now the
patient can be hypothyroid.
So it's going to
be necessary that when
you start patients on
amiodarone, you've got
to do a liver function
look. You've got to
do a thyroid panel.
The other thing, since
it's iodinated, it's
going to affect the skin.
It seems to be that the
drug interacts with the
melanin in the skin.
And that can lead to this
condition where patients
can appear bluish and
that's known as smurf skin.
Corneal deposits is when
the patient now will start
to feel changes in vision
because there is an opacity
and that has to do with
the fact that this drug
accumulated in the cornea, in
the lysosomes of the cornea.
So then amiodarone can
cause a pulmonary fibrosis.
And what's happening
here is that in the
lungs, there's going to
be damage to the type 2
pneumocytes. And that's
an immunological reaction.
And that's going to lead to a
decrease in
surfactant production.
So at baseline and yearly,
you want to do a chest x-ray.
Some cases you may
want to do a pulmonary
function test. You may
want to be very careful if
the patient is using
tobacco products as well.
And then if they
develop this issue,
you have to stop the medication
and administer glucocorticoids.
Again, this is an
immune reaction.
Other drugs that cause
pulmonary fibrosis,
it's worth reviewing
this, is bleomycin,
basulfan, and
methotrexate, which
are considered to
be antineoplastics.
Methotrexate is used for RA.
And nitrofurantoin, which
you'll see a little bit
later, can be used for
urinary tract infections.
And this is just a
changeover, what hyperplasia
of type 2 pneumocytes
will look like.
So the other class 3
drugs, we have droneterone,
which sounds like amiodarone,
but it has no iodine. So
we would not be as concerned
with the thyroid issue
or the changes in the skin
or the corneal deposits.
Soda law, as the name says,
does have non-selective
beta adrenergic blockade.
So it could be
considered in the class 2
group with the beta blockers,
but it's put in class
3 because this one does
have an effect on the
potassium channels. It
causes repolarization.
It has an effect at
the action potential,
prolonging action potential.
It can be used for
AFib treatment.
And then the last two are
dofidolide and imbutilide.
These two are interesting.
They're going to,
of the others,
slow cardiac repolarization.
And due to the fact that
they have this slow defect,
they're going to raise
the QT rather nicely.
And that would mean
that if we give this
medication, we want to
do it under surveillance.
They have to be
monitored, these
patients, for about four hours.
They have to do continuous
EKGs to watch that QT interval.
Class 4 are the calcium
channel blockers.
They will increase
the refractory period,
especially in the AV
node. These are just
like beta blockers or
AV node suppressants.
As mentioned early
in the lecture,
they're going to
work at the shoulder.
They're going to slow
the inward calcium
current that happens
between 0 and 2.
Okay, the shoulder
or the plateau.
They will decrease
the phase 4 slope in
the pacemaker and
the AV node as well.
Okay, and I showed you
that picture early on.
They will prevent
supraventricular
tachycardia. They can
be used for AFib in
patients that cannot
tolerate beta blockers.
And these drugs in this
arrhythmia lecture is
going to be rapamil and
diltiazem, not dipenes. And
the reason why is that,
remember, with the
dipenes, they're going to
work in the arterial role.
They're going to relax
arterial smooth muscle.
That's good. They're
going to lower blood
pressure. But we
know, especially the
earlier dipines like
nifedipine, nicarpedine,
when your blood pressure
goes down significantly,
the body always wants to
go back to what it was.
so they can invoke sympathetics
through the baroreceptor
reflex mechanism and that
can lead to tachycardia
you don't want that to
happen in somebody that is
getting treated for an
arrhythmia that's why verapamil
and diltiazem are the ones
we use they do have some
effects in the arterial
but not significant they're
more for the heart, the SA
and the AV node so calcium
comes into the cell it binds
to calmodulin, it's binding
protein, you activate
myosin light chain kinase,
that phosphorylates
everything, and then when
you pair up with actin
and myosin, you get
contraction. That's what's
happening in the vessels.
one thing to note is that
when we talk about the
tachycardia and the edema
again that is for the dipines
because not only are you
invoking baroreceptor reflex
mechanism with the dipines
you're also invoking renin
and when that happens
you're also increasing
aldosterone, and that's going
to collect more sodium and
water from the kidney to
raise your blood pressure,
and that's where the edema
is coming from. This will
not happen with berapamil
and diltiazem. If anything,
bradycardia is the most likely
adverse effect of these two.
Constipation can happen,
and actually berapamil is
the most, and that's because
if you're thinking about
calcium block in the gut,
it's not going to move
the smooth muscle. So you're
going to get a decrease
in peristalsis. Patients
can become constipated.
Gingival overgrowth, what
is that about? Well, you're
increasing fibroblasts in
the mouth and that's going
to increase collagen
deposition and that's why those
gums become enlarged. Now
with grapefruit juice, this
is interesting because with
grapefruit juice, you're
going to inhibit the metabolism
of rapamyl endotiazem.
And that would mean that
you would probably get
higher levels and that would
lead again to bradycardia.
So digoxin is a very
interesting drug. I will
say that I will revisit
this in CHF because
for years CHF was
maintained with digoxin.
But there are several things
that limit its use and
it was found to actually
not help with the mortality.
So for CHF, you're going
to see that it's ACE
inhibitors or ARBs and
there might be beta
blockers also. But
digoxin is really worth
knowing because there's
a lot that can be tested
and there's a lot to
know clinically here.
Digoxin has two mechanisms.
Number one,
for this lecture, it
has a vagal effect.
It can induce
parasympathetic mechanism.
So if you are inducing
parasympathetic,
you're negative
coronotropic. It's going to
lower heart rate and
lower AV node action.
So digoxin does have a benefit
at reducing AV
node suppression.
But digoxin, and this was
important for those patients
that were using this for
CHF, digoxin has positive
inotropic effects. And the
reason being is that it
blocks an enzyme known as
sodium-potassium ATPase.
And when that enzyme is
blocked, as you can see,
you're not going to have
this exchange of sodium and
potassium. and that by
virtue will affect the sodium
-calcium exchanger to
where sodium is now in the
cell, it's not being pumped
out and now calcium has no
gradient so calcium is
going to stay in the heart
and with that it's going
to bind again and cause
the destroyer with actin
and myosin and you're going
to get a positive
inotropic effect And that
means you're increasing
contractility. And that would
have been a benefit to
those patients with CHF.
Digoxin is sometimes known
as digitalis. It has a
long half-life. It has a
narrow therapeutic index.
So just an extra tablet or two
can put your
patient at toxicity.
Negative coronotropic.
it reduces the heart
rate because it turns
on parasympathetic tone.
Positive inotropic,
due to this mechanism, it
improves contractility.
But one of the issues
is that it does increase
after depolarizations.
And I'll explain that
in a moment. And that
was early in the lecture,
I talked about delayed
after depolarizations.
This comes after phase four.
And that has to
do with calcium.
Digitalis comes from
a plant known as
foxglove. And it's
right there. It
blooms in the spring.
It's very pretty.
One thing to note
about it, and I'll talk
about it now with the
adverse effect, There's
this whole idea of
xanthopsia. But anyway,
digoxin can cause problems with
the GI, nausea,
vomiting, diarrhea.
Patients can experience
a loss of appetite.
Ventricular arrhythmias,
and that has to
do with the delayed
after depolarization.
This happens especially when
the patient has a change
in electrolytes. So back in
the day when patients had
CHF, they were given
digoxin, and most likely, if
they were at that point that
they needed digoxin, they
were probably in the state
where they had lots of edema.
and we use diuretics for
the edema now but the
issue is that if you become
hypokalemic because usually
with CHF we got to use something
that is a high capacity
diuretic and that's going
to be a loop because
remember loops get rid of
lots of fluid but they also
carry out everything with
it. Calcium, magnesium, and
potassium. What would happen
is that the low potassium
would have an even
greater effect on this
enzyme. And you would see
that there would be almost
like a super surge of
calcium in the cell.
And that would lead now
to the person having
and after depolarization,
after phase 4.
So the one thing to know
is if the patient needs
to be put on digoxin
and there'll still be
some cases that would
need it, you have to make
sure that the patient's
electrolytes are normal.
The other thing is the
vision changes, where in
toxicity, patients can
see yellow in their visual
field. They'll see an
object and it'll appear
to be yellowish. That
is known as xanthopsia.
And this effect
seems to be due to
the fact that DIG
can inhibit sodium
potassium ATPase in
the retina cells.
This is sometimes
known as the the
Van Gogh effect of
digoxin toxicity.
And the way it's said
that in some of Van Gogh's
paintings that were yellow,
they say that he was using
digitalis for his seizures.
And as a matter of fact,
in one of the paintings,
there is a picture of the
foxglove pant. Whether
that's true or not, I don't
know, but it did help me
remember this toxicity when I
was in school and it may
help with you all as well.
The Jackson has an
estrogen backbone. So
there are some cases
where patients can
experience gynecomastia.
So that could translate
into enlarged chest
or a change in libido.
Drug interaction is very big.
DIG is a weak acid. When
you give an antacid,
what you're doing is
you're creating a basic
environment. So this
acetic drug will ionize.
Ionized means it
doesn't get through
because you want
everything non-ionized.
Cholesthyramine, they may
be a decrease in absorption
because you're reducing
enterohepatic circulation.
So in that case, the digoxin
would not be absorbed.
So the way we would manage
those two is just spacing
out the drug apart from
each other by several hours.
Amiodarone may inhibit
the metabolism of digoxin.
And then verapamil and
quinidine affect the elimination
because in the
kidney, they inhibit p
-glycoprotein. So digoxin may
have a decreased clearance.
Renal impairment is
important because back
again, when you're thinking
about CHF patients,
they tend to be older.
There's going to be some
degree of change in
their renal function,
and that too can delay
elimination of digoxin.
In an overdose, and the
drug has not been in
circulation, you can bind it
with DigFab, and that brand
name is Digibind. So what
that does, in essence,
it captures the unabsorbed
digoxin, so it can be
excreted. But if that drug
has been absorbed in its
circulation, you need
to start watching the
electrolytes. And the way
we manage the toxicity is to
give magnesium. And magnesium
is very interesting.
This ion will prevent calcium
influx into the cells.
on an EKG digoxin will
show an increase in PR
interval and that makes
sense because that
corresponds to a reduced
AV node and digoxin is
an AV node suppressant
the other thing is that
there may be something
called a hockey stick
configuration where
there is an ST depression
ST happens in between QRS
and the T wave. So you might
see that the patient may not
have toxicity. That might
be just showing you that
the patient is on digoxin.
Adenosine. It's a very
exciting medication
because it gets injected.
It works within seconds,
and it terminates a
PSVT rather quickly.
what's its mechanism well
it looks a little bit like
what we saw before because
number one it has a g
inhibitory receptor
mechanism just like what we
saw with acetylcholine where
adenosine binds and it's
going to decrease
adenocyclase and cyclic AMP
that's going to lower the
impulse through the AV node
here, dromotropic, and
it's going to decrease the
heart rate. So by giving
that, the patient's arrhythmia
has been terminated,
and that's a good thing.
However, there is a couple
of adverse effects that will
happen. Number one, they'll
get a termination of the
arrhythmia, but they're
going to have a vasodilation
that happens. Their blood
pressure is going to go down.
they may feel a little bit
flushed. The reason being
is through this mechanism
that involves G-stimulatory.
That will increase
adenyl cyclase,
increasing cyclic AMP,
and that's going to
relax the smooth muscle.
So it makes sense that that
patient will experience that
flushing and that lowering
of blood pressure. The
other thing that happens is
through a GQ mechanism.
Remember, Remember, GQ increases
IP3 and DAG, and it causes
an increase in calcium in.
That's going to cause
bronchoconstriction.
So oftentimes,
after adenosine is
given, patients are
going to feel somewhat
of a wheezing. And that
might be a little
bit of an anxiety for
them, but that effect
does not last long.
The way I remember
adenosine is theophylline.
Theophylline you will study
later in the semester.
Theophylline is a bronchodilator
which is not widely
used because it does have
certain effects that can
increase heart rate. And
that's because they're
opposites. So with
theophylline, okay, an adenosine
blocker, that drug is going
to cause bronchodilation.
Okay, and that helps somebody
who has asthma or even COPD.
The thing about adenosine
block is that if you overdose,
on theophylline, that G
-inhibitory effect of adenosine
now becomes G-stimulatory.
So if you overdose
on theophylline, you're
probably going to have a
cardiac arrhythmia. So hence,
these two are opposites.
Theophylline is
interesting because it
does come from theobromine,
which is pretty
much the active
ingredient of caffeine.
So it does make sense.
You'll see later, too, when
patients take theophylline,
they can get stimulated
because of that effect. When
you drink lots of caffeine,
sometimes people can
experience some palpitations,
and that is due to the fact
of the adenosine block.
So just to summarize,
AB node suppressants,
diltiazim, rarapamil,
not the diapines.
adenosine through its
G-inhibitory mechanism,
digoxin because it has
parasympathetic effects,
and then beta blockers
because they're blocking
norepinephrine on the beta
-1 receptors of the heart.
So magnesium.
This is an EKG of torsades.
magnesium can be given for
this condition and it can
also be used for dig delayed
after depolarizations why
because it's going to
inhibit the influx of calcium
into the cytosol and the
reason why you're having those
delayed after depolarizations
is due to that increase
in calcium so the one thing
we want is calcium out
and then just a little bit
about potassium we talked
about the T waves on the
EKG. But just to summarize,
hypokalemia.
When the person is
hypokalemic, you're
going to slow
repolarization. And
that is going to
either translate into
after depolarization, after
phase three, or delayed
after phase four. And the
delayed has to do with
the fact that you're
increasing calcium into the
cell. You're causing an
increase in contractility.
Being hyperkalemic
is a little bit
different where you're
going to depress
the action in the SA
and the AV node and
you're also going to
decrease the action
potential duration. And
you can see that here
at three. The line
goes here to the left.
So being careful with
potassium is very, very
important when we're talking
about cardiology. And many
of these drugs do affect
potassium. We said that
already. ACE inhibitors
and ARBs and alloscirin and
spironolactone can
cause hyperkalemia. And
the diuretics, which
are widely used even
for, hypertension can
cause hyperkalemia.
So again, just to summarize
with digoxin, when you're
blocking the sodium ATPase
and you're hypokalemic,
you're going to have a
greater block of this enzyme,
which means that all of
this sodium staying in is
going to shuttle in calcium
with it and it's going to
cause a positive inotropic
effect, increase in
contraction, and that will
result, as you can see here,
in a delayed after
depolarization.
Ivorbradine is considered
to be an interesting
medication. just as the
name says if you want a clue
on how to remember Ivor
Braden's adverse effects
is going to be bradycardia
as the name shows. This
medication is going to
block a channel known as
the IF channels, or the
funny current in the heart.
It will do most of its
action in the SA node. So
it's going to work
specifically in the pacemaker.
And I will say it's
not affecting the
duration of the action
potential. So it's
not having an effect
on repolarization.
on conduction.
We can use this medication
for congestive heart failure,
some cases of stable
angina, and those
people who have arrhythmias and
can't be managed with
the beta blocker.
Some of the adverse
effects, as I
mentioned before,
looking at the name,
it's going to cause bradycardia.
It hasn't been studied
well in pregnancy, so that
is a contraindication.
When you have a SIP inhibitor,
so again, grapefruit
juice will raise the level
of iverbradine and
cause more bradycardia.
And then the vision
changes is worthy of
explaining. Since
iverbradine blocks the funny
channels in the hearts
pacemaker, in the retina,
there are channels
that are known as IH.
And iverbradine blocks IH.
And this channel is responsible
for filtering light.
So if you're blocking
that, what tends to happen
is that patients can
start to see bright spots
in their visual field.
It's known as phosphine.
So again, that would
be something that
the patient needs
to be warned about.
So again,
specifically for
the funny channels
in the pacemaker,
not much is happening
with conduction
or repolarization.
And that's really all I can
say about this medication.
Wolf Parkinson's
white is considered
to be an arrhythmia
that comes from
the formation of an
accessory pathway.
And that is known
as the bundle of
Kent. okay and here
basically we want to
have to have some
type of procedure
but one thing to
note when we manage
this condition with medication
especially if they
have AFib you don't
want to give an AV
node suppressant
And the reason being is
that the impulse, instead
of going to the AV node,
if you're suppressing the
action here with an AV
node suppressant, it's most
likely the impulse is going
to go back to the bundle
of Kent. And there's no
filtering capacity, and
that would mean that the
patient's heart rate can
be anywhere between 200
and 300 beats per minute.
So what can be used is
procainamide, which inhibits
the initiation of the
impulse, or amiodarone, which
will increase the refractory
period. Those are the
two that you could use if
you had a patient with Wolf
-Parkinson-White and AFib.
Those are the two drugs.
And as you can see, in
Wolf-Parkinson-White,
there's the appearance
of delta waves.
So in summary, for
sinus tachycardia, we
want to give a beta
blocker or a calcium
channel blocker that is
going to decrease phase
4, the slope of phase
4, the slope there.
AFib, you can
give any of these.
PSVT, adenosine,
AV block, you can
give atropine.
VTAC, you can give 1,
3, or 1B if the patient
had an ischemia. for
torsades, magnesium mainly,
and then tricyclics, as I
said, sodium bicarbonate.
I'm not going to test
you this on the exam.
I'm going to ask you to
be more familiar with the
main mechanisms and the
main adverse effects.
So if I had to ask you
something on amiodarone,
you probably know that I
will ask something about
pulmonary fibrosis,
changes in thyroid, etc.
So this is a review question
from the lipid lecture.
So very quickly, we have
a 65-year-old female
presenting to the clinic
with chest pain on
exertion, and she has a
history of type 2 diabetes
and smokes two packs of
cigarettes per day. Her
pulse is 74 and blood
pressure is 155 over 105.
And her LDL is 180
and she's prescribed a
medication that inhibits
the hepatic production
of circulating
molecules implicated in
the pathogenesis of
coronary artery disease.
the concomitant use of
gemfibrazole with this
medication would increase
the incidence of. So first
of all for LDL if we're
looking at the mechanism
of the drug and the fact
that it's working in
the liver to stop
production of cholesterol my
best bet is she's probably
given a statin drug.
And we also are saying if
she's given gemfibrazole
and that's sometimes
happens if the patient's
triglycerides are greater than
500. Because in that case,
you'll be at a high risk
of getting pancreatitis.
But on a normal given day,
we tend not to want to give
fibrates with statins or
even fibrates with niacin.
We try not to double
up on these medications
unless we need to. And
the reason being is
that the patient can
have an adverse effect.
So what is the adverse
effect? Well, is it
bradycardia? I'm going
to say no. If anything,
I would be more concerned with
bradycardia
happening with, say,
a beta blocker or
verapamil diltiazem.
GI bleed, if anything,
I would be more
concerned with maybe
aspirin causing a GI bleed.
Hyperkalemia,
okay, so ACE inhibitors,
ARBs, spironolactone.
Metabolic alkalosis,
that can result from
diuretics, mainly the
thiazides and the loops.
Myoglobinuria, that could
be the right answer because
pancreatitis actually
would be what we would want
to prevent happening in those
patients that have really
high triglycerides level.
So I'm going to say that
E is the best answer. And
the reason being is that
if you give a fibrate with
the statin or statin with
niacin, you do run the risk
that the patient can have
an increase in myalgia.
And if you get breakdown,
of the muscle, the patient,
aside from feeling the
aches and pains, can have a
high creatine kinase level.
And they may also
show urine that is
tea colored. So I
would say that the
best answer is E
for this question.
Thank you for your
attention. And I do have a
question review. It may
take a little longer for
you, but I will say
that the question review
will help with reviewing
some of these concepts,
and I do say that they're
very important. But
until then, thank you,
and have a great week.